<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A perpetual league of mutual defence and allyance between his Majesty, and the Estates General of the United Provinces of the Low Countries together with a confirmation of the Articles of Commerce, agreed upon by the Treaty of Breda. / Published by his Majesties command.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1668</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B02101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3197</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R171256</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52614565</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52614565</idno>
            <idno type="VID">175798</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B02101)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 175798)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2751:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A perpetual league of mutual defence and allyance between his Majesty, and the Estates General of the United Provinces of the Low Countries together with a confirmation of the Articles of Commerce, agreed upon by the Treaty of Breda. / Published by his Majesties command.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
                  <author>United Provinces of the Netherlands. Staten Generaal.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Re-printed by Evan Tyler ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.LXVIII. [1668]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Initial letter.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through with loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Treaty of Breda (1667).</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Foreign relations --  Netherlands --  Sources.</term>
               <term>Netherlands --  Foreign relations --  Great Britain --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:175798:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Perpetual LEAGUE OF <hi>Mutual Defence and Allyance</hi> BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY, AND THE ESTATES GENERAL Of the <hi>UNITED PROVINCES</hi> Of the Low-COUNTRIES: Together With a Confirmation of the <hi>Articles of Commerce,</hi> agreed upon by th Treaty at <hi>Breda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Re-printed by <hi>Evan Tyler,</hi> Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty, M.DC.LXVIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:175798:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:175798:2"/>
            <head>A perpetual League of mutual Defence and Alliance between His Majeſty, and the Eſtates General of the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces</hi> of the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries;</hi> Together with a Confirmation of the Articles of Commerce, agreed upon by the Treaty at <hi>Breda.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas by the late Treaty concluded at <hi>Breda,</hi> between the moſt Serene and moſt Potent Prince and Lord <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, King of <hi>Great Britain</hi> on the one part, and the High and Mighty Lords the States Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the <hi>United Provinces</hi> on the other part, the ancient Friendſhip and good Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency between the two Nations has by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God been reſtored; And for the taking away all occaſions of new Differences for the future, and for preventing ſuch accidents as might happen between the Subjects of either ſide to the diſturbance of the ſaid Amity and good Correſpondence; certain Rules and Articles of Commerce and Navigation were then agreed upon, and particularly in the 11. Article of the ſaid Treaty it was agreed, That the ſaid Lord the King, and the ſaid Lords the States General ſhould be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:175798:3"/>and remain Friends, Confederates and Allyes, for the defending the Rights and Priviledges of each others Subjects, againſt all perſons whatſoever, who ſhould endeavour by Land or Sea to diſturb the Peace of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther State, or who being Inhabitants in eithers Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions ſhould be declared Publick Enemies of either State: But yet no particular mention being there made of the Aids and Succours wherewith one Party ſhould in ſuch caſe be oblieged to aſſiſt the other; And as well the ſaid King, as the ſaid States General, reſolving to ſtrengthen and to bring yet to further perfection the ſaid Agreements, have agreed in the firſt and principal place to confirm, as by theſe preſents they do confirm, the ſaid Treaty concluded at <hi>Breda,</hi> and the ſaid Rules and Articles of Commerce thereto belonging, mutually obliging themſelves to a ſincere and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual obſervation of them, and to cauſe them to be ſtrictly and religiouſly obſerved and fulfilled by the Subjects on either ſide, according to the genuine ſenſe and meaning of the ſaid Treaty, and the Articles therein contained. And further for aſcertaining the Succours to be mutually given, which was omitted in the ſaid Treaty as aforeſaid, as well to improve and encreaſe the Friendſhip that is between the ſaid Lord the King, and the ſaid Lords the States General, as for ſeaſonably providing by a cloſer Union and Alliance for the mutual ſafety and defence of each State againſt the Hoſtile attempts and practices of whomſoever, and under what pretence ſoever, We whoſe names are underwritten, by vertue of the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Commiſſions to Us granted, and which are to be inſerted in the cloſe hereof, have agreed and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:175798:3"/>concluded, That the ſaid Lord the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the ſaid Lords the States General of the <hi>United Netherlands,</hi> ſhall be, and by vertue of theſe Preſents they are mutually allied, united and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate in a perpetual Defenſive League, on the Terms and Conditions following.</p>
            <div n="1" type="terms_and_conditions">
               <head>I.</head>
               <p>That if any Prince or State, or any other of what condition ſoever, none excepted, ſhall under any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence whatſoever, invade, or endeavour to invade the Territories, Countries, or any places whatſoever, under the Dominion of the ſaid King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> or exerciſe any other act of Hoſtility, either by Land or Sea, againſt the ſaid Lord the King, or his Subjects; the ſaid Lords the States General ſhall be oblieged, and by vertue of theſe Preſents they are oblieged for the Oppoſing, Suppreſſing or Repelling of ſuch Attempts, and acts of Hoſtility, and for obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reparation of damages ſuſtained thereby, to aſſiſt the ſaid Lord the King with fourty Ships of War well equipped, of which 14 to carry between 60 and 80 Guns, and 400 men apiece one with another: Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen others, from 40 to 60 Guns, and at leaſt 300 men apiece one with another; and none of the reſt to carry leſs then 36 Guns, and 150 men: As alſo with 6000 Foot, and 400 Horſe, or the juſt value in Money of ſuch ſuccour, at the choice of the ſaid Lord the King, or with ſuch part of the ſaid ſuccour, or the value of it in Money, as the ſaid Lord the King ſhall deſire; the ſaid ſuccours to be given within the ſpace of ſix weeks after they ſhall be required; and the ſaid Lord the King to refund and pay back all the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:175798:4"/>Charges to the ſaid Lords the States within three years after the end of the War.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="terms_and_conditions">
               <head>II.</head>
               <p>That if any Prince or State, or any other who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he be, none excepted, ſhall upon any pretence whatſoever, invade or endeavour to invade the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces,</hi> or any places under the Dominion of the ſaid Lords the States General, or where they have a Garriſon, or ſhall exerciſe any other act of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility by Sea or Land, againſt the ſaid Lords the States General, or their Subjects, The ſaid Lord the King ſhall be obliged, and by vertue of theſe Preſents he is obliged for the oppoſing, ſuppreſſing and repelling the ſaid Attempts and Acts of Hoſtility, and for ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining reparation of damages thereby received, to aſſiſt the ſaid Lords the States with 40 Ships of War well equipped, of which number 14 to carry between 60 and 80 Guns, and 400 men apiece one with another; Fourteen others from 40 to 60 Guns, and at leaſt 300 men one with another, and none of the reſt to carry leſs then 36 Guns, and 150 Men; and alſo with 6000 Foot and 400 Horſe, or a juſt value in Money for ſuch ſuccour, at the choice of the ſaid Lords the States, or with ſuch part of the ſaid ſuccour, or the value of it in Money as they ſhall deſire; the ſaid ſuccour to be given within the ſpace of ſix weeks after it ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; and the ſaid Lords the States General to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fund and pay back to the ſaid Lord the King, all Charges within three years after the end of the War.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="terms_and_conditions">
               <head>III.</head>
               <p>The ſaid Ships of War, and the Auxiliary Forces of Horſe and Foot, together with the Captains of Ships
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:175798:4"/>and Commanders of thoſe Forces, and other the inferior Officers, ſhall be under the Command of the party injur'd, and ſhall obey ſuch Orders as they ſhall receive from him or them who ſhall have the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in chief of his Forces by Sea or Land.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="terms_and_conditions">
               <head>IIII.</head>
               <p>And for the better ſettling and agreeing an exact Rule for computing the Charges which are to be paid back within 3 years after the War, or the value in ready Money, which poſſibly may have been choſen by the party injured, in lieu of all, or part of the ſaid Ships, and Forces of Horſe and Foot, It has been thought fit that the Charges of 14 Ships, from 60 to 80 Guns, well equipped, ſhall be eſtimated at the rate of eighteen thouſand ſix hundred ſixty and ſix pounds Sterling, or Engliſh Money, by the Month; and thoſe 14 from 43 to 60 Guns, at fourteen thouſand pounds Sterling; and the other 12 at ſix thouſand pounds of the ſame Money. That the 6000 Foot be valued at 7500 l. Sterling, and the 400 Horſe at one thouſand and forty pounds of like Money, by the month. The ſaid Summes to be paid by the ſaid Lord the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> at <hi>London;</hi> and by the Lords the <hi>States Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> according to the courſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change at the time when ſuch Payments ſhall become due: But for the Foot above-mentioned, there ſhall for the firſt Month be paid the ſumme of 6000 l. Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, over and above, that ſumme being found neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the raiſing of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="terms_and_conditions">
               <head>V.</head>
               <p>This League, with all and every thing therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ſhall be Confirmed and Ratified by the ſaid
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:175798:5"/>Lord the King of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and the ſaid Lords the States General of the <hi>United Provinces,</hi> by Letters Patents on each ſide, under their Great Seals, in due and authentick Form, within the ſpace of 4 Weeks next enſuing, or ſooner if it may be done: And the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Ratification interchangeably delivered within the ſame time.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <hi>At the</hi> Hague, <date>13/23 January, 1668.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>De Gellicom.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Aſperen.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johan de-Witte.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Van Cromon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Adolph V. Unkel.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Johan V. Schrieck.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Isbrandts.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
